OK, let's get us started.
Welcome everyone.
I'm extremely happy to be back as a lecturer in this course again.
Today we're going to discuss another exciting topics, single instruction, multiple data
architectures, which has been used a lot in today's computing and actually cause a lot of
innovations and extremely high performance that we are seeing today for machine learning.
For example, GPUs are actually a prime example of architectures that they are heavily using this
SIMD paradigm.
We're going to get to GPUs also hopefully next week, but today we're going to go into fundamentals
of SIMD architectures to understand how they are working.
So just as a reminder, this is actually kind of like other execution paradigm that we've been
looking into it and we kind of covered all of all these Grays.
We haven't covered decoupled access execute, which they're going to be actually a premiere at 5:15
today.
I mean you can watch it today or later about this topic decoupled access Execute.
This architecture decoupled access execute has been introduced initially in order to reduce the
overhead of out of order machine but later on it has been used a lot in today's accelerators like
for example Google TPU which has been we have look into it in the previous lectures in systolic
arrays Google TPU.
Actually they are also using this decoupled access execute, which it's another example that some of
the ideas that have been developed in the past and they didn't get into the general purpose
computing.
Now they are actually finding their ways into more specialised computing like accelerators that
we've seen today.
So it's a nice topic and I recommend everyone to check it.
It's an optional lecture, but if you're interested, please check it.
OK.
And we have some readings for today and next week.
So you can also check these readings.
OK?
So we're going to talk about CMD, which the goal is to exploit data level parallelism, the
parallelism that we have among our data.
Like we have extreme amount of piece pieces of data, like 1,000,000 pieces of data.
And then you want to do similar operations among them.
Like think about, you want to add 2 extremely large arrays.
So the whole, the only operation that you want to do is addition, but you want to do this addition
across millions of operands of these two arrays.
So in that case, we are actually considering this regular data parallelise that SIMD architectures
are very good at exploiting that.
And also we're going to get to GPS later and we're going to see how GPS are connected to SIMD
architectures.
But today we're going to start with exploiting regular or data parallelise.
So before going to that, I want to show you this, Flynn's taxonomy of computers.
I'm not sure if you have seen it before in this course.
Is it the first time for you to see Flynn taxonomy?
OK, so Flynn actually categorised computers based on how many instructions are doing what and how
many pieces of data in four groups.
The first group is SISD which is single instruction operates on single data element and this
actually has been you know the computer architectures that we have seen this in this course a lot
like the single cycle processor pipeline, multi cycle, out of order machine, all of them are SISD,
OK.
Another group is single instruction operates on multiple data elements.
So which is going to be the topic of today's lecture.
So you have 1 instruction and then you want to operate this instruction across 1000 millions of or
billions of data elements.
And the two prime example of SIMD machine are actually array processor and vector processor.
Today's machine are actually combining these two array and vector.
What we're going to see distinguishing between them and then how we're going to combine these two
paradigm.
Another category is MISD which is multiple instructions operate on single data elements.
The closest form to MIC is actually systolic array processor or also streaming processor where it's
historic array you are fetching a data elements and by moving that data elements across different
functional units you are doing different operations on that data elements essentially.
So, yeah, so that's the closest form to MIC and.
MIMD which is multiple instructions operate on multiple data elements essentially like parallel
computer, multi processor, multi threaded processor.
All these things are MIMD and I should also say that today's architectures are actually combining
all these paradigms.
So when you look at your modern processors, they they have like the core is SISD and they have you
have multiple cores and each core also is capable of running multiple threads.
So they are actually also doing MIMD in your core.
Also you have some pipeline specific for SIMD instructions.
So in your core also you have SIMD paradigm and you might also have some accelerators in your in
your system on chip which is based on systolic array like Google TPO for example.
And then they are also MISD.
So in the end, we are actually combining these two, these 4 paradigms in today's computer
architecture.
Makes sense.
OK, so if you want to learn more about this Flynn's taxonomy, I would recommend you check this
paper.
It's a beautiful paper.
I Love Actually, I love it.
And the first time I look into it.
So this is the picture from this paper about MISD.
So you can see that this our data storage and we have instruction storage in different units and
essentially when you fetch data, you are moving this data through different execution unit and each
execution unit is doing some part of the total, you know, computation on that piece of data.
So that's the multiple instruction single data.
And as I said, it's similar to a generalised Sysolig array.
And if you're interested, you can also check the lecture that we have actually presented last week
on Sysolig array architectures.
But in SIMD example from fleeing, essentially you have instruction storage.
So you've essentially you fetch instruction and this instruction is going to fit into different data
elements.
There might be some communication between the different data elements is actually limited
communication.
But in reality the most you are basically you're relying on, you don't have that much communication
between different elements.
So you you want to have ideally you want to have embarrassingly parallel application that the
instruction that you are doing across all these elements, data elements, they don't have anything
to do with each other.
So they can actually be executed completely independently.
With that you can actually maximise your performance by parallelising all these execution.
So this is actually similar to an array processor which we're going to see today.
OK, so before that let's get discuss about this data parallelist that we are talking about.
So this actually the concurrency arises from performing the same operation on different pieces of
data which is single instruction multiple data.
An example could be like array addition or dot product of 2 vectors, also matrix matrix
multiplication.
And that's why why we are using a lot of SIMD paradigm for doing matrix matrix multiplication also
for doing machine learning accelerators.
So one of the core kernel in in machine learning is also doing a lot of matrix matrix multiplication
and that's why they are actually having a lot of regular data parallelies and that's why SIMD
architectures are very good at accelerating these machine learning applications.
It's also a fun to contrast this data parallelise with other type of parallelise like data flow.
So data flow is just to remind you concurrency arises from executing different operations in
parallel in a data-driven manner.
Also to contrast with threads parallelise or control parallelise which concurrency arises from
executing different threads of control in parallel where in SIMD or in data parallelise SIMD
explores operation level parallelism on different data.
So it's actually a very specific form of instruction level parallel.
So you have think about it like as like to get back to the example I said, so you have two big
arrays and you want to just add these two arrays element wise.
So you have like considering you have millions of data elements, you have millions of instructions,
millions of addition instructions and all these addition instructions are actually and not
dependent on each other because they can operate in parallel.
So that's actually instruction level parallelis but very specific form of ILP which the fact that
all these instructions should be the same.
So it's not similar to out of order machine that you would try to explode ILP there you can have
different instructions actually, but here the whole instructions are the same and you just want to
parallelise the execution of that.
Make sense?
Yes.
But there's still ways to use SMD to have something, well, has still some dependence your previous
values.
And there are some techniques like for example, in parallel programming, you can calculate
everything in parallel, but then add things into which the value from previous dependencies.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
For example, you're talking about reduction.
You, you do some like for dot, for dot, you do multiplication and then you need to do a reduction
sum.
That's true.
But once you are doing this multiplication, for example, there is no dependency.
In some later levels of the computation, you might have some dependency which you need to be careful
about that of course, and that would limit your parallelism.
In the end we're going to get to and the law also very soon, which in the end the old parallel
performance, they are actually limited by the serial portion of the application, which when you
want to do reduction time, you're essentially doing some serial operation essentially that, but
we're going to get to that.
OK, very good.
So SIMD processing paradigm, single instruction operates on multiple data elements in time or in a
space.
So we're going to get to that very soon with the example.
So multiple processing elements or execution units, but these processing elements can be actually
located in in different time or in different space.
So you know, there is a nice picture that you're going to get to that easily.
So in the end here we have this time space duality for CMD processing paradigm, which in the end we
can distinguish between array processing and vector processing.
So in array processor instruction operates on multiple data elements at the same time using
different spaces processing elements.
So think about it that you have several processing elements that they are capable of doing
everything like all these processing elements are capable of doing load operation, addition,
multiplication, store like all all the instruction that you have in your own in your ISA and you
just put them, you know, in parallel.
And so in your SIMD operation, you're just feeding your data in all these processing elements.
OK, so that that's kind of array processor and that's why we are talking about you know we have
different processing elements in different space.
So you are doing the same operation like addition at the same time.
But in order to be able to do the same operation at the same time you need to have copy of that
functional unit.
So that's why you need to copy all these functional units in space such that you able to do that
operation in parallel.
Whereas in vector processor instruction operates on multiple data elements in consecutive time
steps.
So now you have a pipeline you know way.
So you have elements that they are capable of doing some specific operations.
For example you have a load unit, you have a store unit, you have addition unit, you have
multiplication.
And then what you do is you basically you are not able to do like all load operation at the same
time because you have only one load unit.
But what you can do is actually pipeline them, pipeline it in a consecutive cycles.
So you do load operation for one vector operation and then next cycle you do the the load for the
other one.
And you basically you have you're doing the same operation at consecutive cycles, but at different
space you're doing you you might be able to do different operations.
So I'm going to show you the example very soon, which going to actually clarify very better so.
But before that, it's important to learn about vector registers.
So in SIMD architecture, whether regardless of using array processor or vector processor, you need
to have vector registers.
And here each register stores a vector and it's basically not a scalar value that we we know about
it.
Like in MIPS for example, we have 3232 bit registers.
But here, for example, you say that, OK, I have 8, let's say 256 bit registers.
And each of these 256 bits are capable of storing some elements of vectors essentially.
So essentially in your vector registers are capable of storing several registers because now you're
operating on vectors.
So for example, here we have some registers that they are, they can hold NM bit values.
So, and that's very important to think about it because you you do need vector registers for the
same reason that we knew we need register file for a scalar operations also here.
OK, so that's the example that I want to show you.
So here we are showing array processor.
So we have different processing elements that they are so four that they are locating at the
different space and each.
Processing elements are capable of doing like all the operations that we have in our IC.
Whereas in vector processor you have different functional units and this functional unit are
specific.
So this one is only doing load and this one is only doing addition and so on and so forth.
OK.
And this is the instruction stream that we want to execute.
So, so the first instruction is like load.
Basically we are loading an array from the memory like a three to zero to a vector register.
Like syntax is not very important here.
Just think about it at a high level.
So you are basically loading 4 elements to your vector register.
OK, so that's loading.
And then you want to add this vector register by one, which is element wise.
So all these four elements that you have in your vector register are going to be incremented by 1
and then you multiply element wise to two and then you restore your vector register to the same
location in the memory.
OK, so that's the code.
And then let's see how we're going to see that how this instruction stream are going to be executed
in these two array processor and vector processor.
OK, Any question regarding the code before I show the OK?
So in array processor essentially at the same time you can do load operation because all these
processing elements are capable of doing load OK.
So you are doing load zero, load one, load 2 and load 3 for these different array elements in
completing parallel and then in the next cycle or next after some cycles depending on your load
latency in the end you can do addition but then addition is also completing parallel and then you
do multiplication and then after some time you can do a store.
OK so for array process actually things are easy everything you can do in parallel.
Whereas in vector processor at the first cycle you can only do load 0 which is loading the first
element of the array.
The next cycle, you can do the load operation for the second element and then you can also do the
addition for the first element.
The next cycle you'll continue loading and also also addition adding the second element and also
multiplication of the first element.
And basically you got the idea.
You now you have this kind of a pipeline for vector processor.
And after some time you basically finish the pipeline.
OK, So at the steady state, meaning that when your vector processor pipeline is also full, you're
going to have 4 instructions at at the same time, right?
So in array processor every time you have 4 instruction at, you know at each cycle.
So that's your throughput essentially in vector processor also when your pipeline is full at the
city state, you're going to also have 4 instructions very similar to, you know, the different
pipelining, you know, paradigm that we've been looking to it in the past.
OK, so here is the actually the.
The access for the time.
So you can see that in array processor we are doing the same operation at the same time, but in
vector processor we are doing different operation at the same time, OK.
And if you also add another access to it, which is a space access, you can see that in array
processor at each space we are doing the same operation.
I'm sorry, different operations because processing elements are capable of doing everything, OK?
So we are able to do different operation at the same space.
Whereas in vector processor, you're doing the same operation at the same space because the fact that
our functional units are capable of doing only one thing, OK, or things that we define for them.
So that's a very, you know, let's say detailed distinguish between the vector processor and array
processor.
In the beginning, actually vector processor were much more, let's say, interesting because you don't
need to add that much overhead like you can get to relatively good performance without, you know,
we, we don't, we don't, we don't be, not be required to add processing elements that they are
capable of doing everything.
So it's good for cost efficiency.
But the RA processor is also good because, you know, they can provide relatively, I mean, good
performance easily.
So then in the end, actually people converge to combining these two paradigm, which we're going to
see actually later also.
But today we're going to see a lot with the vector processor.
But a lot of things that we're going to discuss in Vector Processor, you can also apply them to.
Array processor, in the end they are not that much different.
Question makes sense, OK, sounds good.
So it's also interesting to think about you know how we want to differentiate this SIMD paradigm
with REALIW which we have been seen also before.
So in REALIW multiple independent operations packed together into a long instruction.
So if you think about it in SIMD, you have a ILP and you are able to pack all, let's say addition,
like here for example, this addition I can pack for addition, OK?
But instead of packing up for addition, I'm going to say that, OK, I know that I'm going to only do
addition.
So I will only put 1 addition, one instruction add.
And then I'm going to use this instruction to operate on multiple data elements.
And that's the key difference.
So by doing that, you are capable of essentially amortising the overhead of fetching and decoding
instructions.
So that's the overhead that you need to bring instruction to the processor.
And by fetching and then decoding and then essentially starting executing.
So, so that's the overhead.
And in CMD architecture, you are capable of amortising this overhead across millions of operations.
So you're fetching only once addition or multiplication and then you're going to execute that
instruction across millions of operands.
And that's what the what I said essentially here in CMD processing.
So for VLIW also you can check the lecture that we have presented last week.
OK, so let's get to some examples about vector processor and how the performance of them could be.
So a vector essentially is A1 dimensional array of numbers and a lot of application in scientific
and commercial programs they use vectors.
And here is an example that for example, yeah, we have a four loop that iterates 50 times.
And in each iteration, essentially we we are restoring the average of the two arrays A&B element
wise in a destination array.
OK, so that's a code, simple code that we have here.
So a vector processor is 1 whose instructions operate on vectors rather than a scalar values.
So that's you what you need to know.
And there are some basic requirements for vector processor.
So basically we need to have loaded store vectors.
So that's why we have vector registers that they contain vectors.
We also need to operate on vectors of different links.
So we should know that like how many operands or like basically we, we should know that essentially
the size of the vector like how many operands you have there.
Because when you load, when you fetch 1 instruction, you know, you should know that how many
instructions for how many operands you need to operate these instructions.
So that's your vector lengths.
So usually there is a register that's in your processor, in your CMD processor that you need to set
before starting.
You know your execution, which is vector lengths.
Another important thing is that that we should know how we need to calculate the next address.
Essentially elements of a vector might be stored apart from each other in memory.
They might be consecutive like like in array for example, like every you know the elements like the
next one.
So you can just you you need to like increment your effective memory address and access the memory
to get your new data.
So that's your vector stride register.
But the they might be also a bit distant.
So they might be like they stand by 10.
So every time you need to add your effective memory address by by 10 to get to the new address, for
example.
So that's the thing that you need to also again set which is vector stride register when you want to
do operation.
So this vector stride example can actually be interesting in matrix multiply.
So we have two matrices A&B that we want to basically multiply them.
And these two are stored in memory in row major order.
So in row major order, meaning that we first essentially fill the the row in the memory and then we
go to the second row.
So the the matrix A element 012 these are consecutive and then we get to element 6 and seven.
And here also in other metrics B which we need to store again the room major order.
So now we want to calculate the multiplication of A&B.
So A is 4/4 by 6 and B is 6 by 10.
So that.
Resulting matrix C is going to be 4 by 10.
OK, so when you want to calculate each destination element of C, you essentially need to do operate
a dot product of a row in A and also a column in B OK, so that's the dot product that you
essentially you need to do your SIMD operation on it.
So now we have this problem.
When we want to load elements of matrix A, our stride is actually one, right?
Because we just go one by one.
But when we want to load elements of matrix B, the stride is 10 because we need to load one column.
So essentially you need to alternate your stride when you want to fetch this A&B and then do the
SIMD operation.
So that's the interesting thing.
We're going to get to that.
Also later regarding we are talking about bank conflicts, but essentially this strike can actually
cause some problems.
Different strikes can cause problems for us.
Any question make sense?
OK.
And if you also store the other way, like call a major order, things are just flip, right?
So for for B is going to be consecutive, but then for a you need to you have a stride of 6 for
example.
OK, so vector vector instruction performs an operation each element in consecutive cycles.
So that's the definition of vector processor.
And also vector functional units are pipeline and each pipeline stage operates on different data
elements.
So that's kind of a summary that what we have discussed.
Another interesting thing is that vector instructions allow deeper pipelines.
Any idea why?
So why we are able to have a deep pipeline for vector instructions for vector process?
Yes.
Time to process each element of it and then the pipeline becomes balanced we can do more strongly
involvement pipeline yeah, maybe it could be also the case, but one of the so there were some let's
say dependency problem in pipeline.
Anyone remind what are the dependency, let's say that we had in pipeline processor that they 'cause
mitigation and like 'cause limitation in the performance.
Yes, branches and also data dependence as well, right?
So in your in your normal pipeline, you different instructions that you're pipelining them.
They are they might be dependent on each other, right?
So you need to do a lot of this interlocking, you know, checking that whether or not I can continue
the pipeline or I need to install the pipeline.
OK.
And usually you, you're avoiding deep pipeline because when you're not able to do that, you need to
flush or you need to do a lot of bubbles your pipeline, which going to cause a lot of performance.
Overhead also control dependence that one of your colleague mentioned like branches when you're
mispredicted, you need to flush some instructions, right?
When your pipeline is deep, the overhead is also much bigger.
So that's why.
But none of them actually are more or less the case in SIMD processor.
We're going to see that in vector processor we don't.
So first of all there is not much dependency across instructions that they are doing on the same
OPRAN sorry instruction that we are doing on a different Oprans.
So these are completely independent.
So we are we don't have data dependence much so we can deep deepen the pipeline.
Another reason is that we don't have that much branches in SIMD processor.
We are handling branches in a different way which we're going to see later also.
So that's why actually array processor are actually heavily pipelined.
So they are much.
So the the depths of pipeline for them is much more compared to the general purpose processor which
they are in the sense of 10 to 20, you know, stage.
But in vector processor they can be actually much more like I, I have I don't have any number on top
of my head, but you can think of it, it can be much more.
So with that you can increase your clock frequency also much more.
So there is no intro vector dependencies which we talk about it, no control flow within a vector.
And also knowing a strong stride allows easy address calculation.
So another thing is that so you know you're a stride before starting the, you know the operation
before loading for example, and then you can start.
Calculating the next address, you know, soon enough you can think of as it also prefetching, which
we're going to also look into it later lectures.
But essentially knowing strides allow us easy, easy loading or even early loading.
So you can start actually calculating the address for next, next, next operas and also bringing them
to the processor to hide some latencies.
So because of these reasons, actually vector instructions allow deeper pipelines for us.
So there are some advantages in vector processor, no dependencies within a vector.
So pipelining and parallelisation work really well and we can have very deep pipeline without the
penalty of deep pipelines.
Each instruction generates a lot of work.
So with that you can amortize the overhead of fetching and decoding on instructions and no need to
explicitly code loops.
So we're going to see that like your loop is going to be considered as a vectorizable partition of
your code.
So you can get rid of your loop completely and just do the essentially vector instruction instead.
We're going to see that with some example.
So no need to explicitly code loops.
And they're also highly regular memory access pattern.
So if you have actually embarrassingly parallel application with like good good amount of data
parallel list, then you can actually have a highly regular memory access pattern.
Like think about this vector vector addition or vector vector dot product or matrix matrix
multiplication.
All memory accesses are kind of actually regular and predictable.
OK.
But when your memory access patterns are not that predictable and can be actually kind of irregular,
like think about pointer chasing, like searching for a key in a in a linked list.
So you don't know.
So you don't know the next address until you load one elements a pointer and decode it to see and
also execute it to see what the address is and then you can fetch another one.
So in that sense, your your memory access pattern is quite irregular.
And in those sense actually vector processor not very good.
So basically that this one brings me to the fact that vector processor actually they work only.
So only is in parentheses because I mean they can work but their performance is terrible.
Like you can actually run pointer chasing also on an array processor of course.
But there is no, let's say motivation for doing that because they don't really provide good
performance for us.
So they work only if paralysis is regular like data and CMD paralysis.
So they are very inefficient if paralysis is irregular like searching a key in a linked list.
And there is a nice writing actually in this in this VLIW paper that Professor Moody also talked
about it I guess last week.
So you can also read here.
Essentially it is actually kind of a critic regarding this SIMD processor.
So basically it says that to program a vector machine, the compiler or hand coder must make the data
structures in the code fit nearly exactly the regular structure beating to the hardware.
So basically the programmer should should know everything how they are mapped to the hardware and
then try to put the data elements kind of nicely such that you can benefit from the performance.
So that's hard to do in the in first place and just as hard to change.
So when you when you modify your hardware, you need to do everything from the scratch essentially.
So, So that's essentially the one of the biggest problem with this processor that the programming of
them is also a kind of headache.
And that's why actually GPUs that they are very successful these days.
They actually use SIMD paradigm, but they fix the problem of programming in a very interesting way,
which we're going to see that next week.
But I would say that that tweak or that idea that they have by fixing the programming model for GPUs
makes them that much successful these days.
Because we've we've had a lot of SIMD processor in the past like Cray, but they didn't at some point
they couldn't really continue even though they had a very good performance.
But programming then was really hard.
And if you cannot program, then you cannot use your machine in the end.
So program model is always very also important.
OK, so you can also read this original paper of VLIW For more information that essentially has a
nice critique about array processor in the paper.
Also, we should not forget Ando's law.
Is it the first time that you're seeing Ando's law?
I didn't know, right?
Yeah, you've, you've done it before.
Yeah, seen it before.
So essentially your our speed up is limited by serial portion, serial bottleneck that we have.
So in Arab you might have very good data parallelise, but then at some point you need to do some
serial operation.
Like for one of your colleague was mentioning about at some point you you need to like sum some of
the elements to get to the final result.
Like in that product, if you think about it, you do parallel multiplication and then you need to Add
all these products right to get the final results of the dot product.
So that addition, you can try to do it in parallel.
You can have a, you can have a reduction sum tree, which in some ways in some layers you're doing
things in parallel.
But in the end that operation is not fully parallel because you need to synchronise and you need to
get to the final edition result.
So that can limit essentially the the performance of the operation that we have, the parallel
program that we have, which is the serial bottleneck, OK.
And you can also check this paper from Amdos.
And if you're interested about seeing how we can accelerate the serial portion of this, you know,
the parallel application, I recommend you checking this, these, these lectures from our advanced
computer architecture that we heavily discuss.
And you know, how, how can we, you know, accelerate the serial bottleneck of the application?
There's a parallel part accelerating that is not, I mean, it's, I'm not saying that it's easy, but
it's also, we know how to do it.
So you can have a lot of multiple a lot of processing elements and you can parallelise the
application or the execution across them.
But the serial part, how are you going to do that, right.
So one way for example would be considering that OK, in your system on chip you have many small
cores that they are very good at executing parallel the parallel part.
But you also have some large cores which they provide by large core you can think of, you know, big
out of order machine, you know, so these large cores are not are costly, but they are good at
accelerating serial portion.
So at some point you can actually when you have a serial bottleneck, you can offload that serial
execution to the large core such that this large core which is actually specifically very good at
serial portion, they accelerate that serial portion.
So if you're interested for more detail, you can actually check this lecture for regarding
bottleneck acceleration, which we had in computer architecture.
OK, so another problem of vector processor is actually memory bandwidth.
So memory bandwidth can easily become a bottleneck.
The reason is that you have you have a deep pipeline, you have a lot of frosting elements or a lot
of functional units.
And essentially you need to feed, feed them with data, you know, you need to keep them busy like
with vector processor.
Think about the steady state that I talk about it.
You need to keep feeding data elements to your vector process or pipeline such that you can get to
the steady state and get a nice throughput out of it.
OK, so that's needs a lot of memory bandwidth and that's why architectures that they are heavily
relying on SIMD they are they they always try to increase memory bandwidth like GPUs, one of the
let's say flagship advertisement that they always have in GPUs like every generation they talk
about the memory bandwidth, how much they increase memory bandwidth by each generation.
So essentially these architecture they really need a lot of memory bandwidth.
So compute and memory operation balance is not maintained usually in CMD processor and data is not
mapped appropriately to memory banks.
So in these two cases memory bandwidth can be can be quickly a bottleneck and then would limit your
performance in the end.
So for the for the first part, compute memory operation balance is not maintained.
People try to like increase memory bandwidth as much as they can and also some cases they try to
limit the compute throughput in some process.
Of course, there is also more fundamental way of doing that, which in Safari we've been also looking
into it by moving compute and memory operation closer to each other, which is we talk about it
processing memory.
So with with that you can actually have much more balance compute and memory bandwidth together.
And for for the second month, basically compiler and programmer can do their best, you know, to map
their data in nicely across different memory banks to avoid bank conflicts as much as possible.
We're going to get.
Bank confident goes with some examples later, but but at some point you're limited.
So you're limited by the by the number of banks that you have.
You're limited especially when you're doing operations on the like the example that we had matrix,
matrix multiplication when you have different strides.
So when you need to deal with different strides, then you have much more.
We have a more difficult problem here.
So in the end, at some point, your compute memory operation are not balanced enough and also your
data may not be mapped appropriately across banks.
So then your memory bandwidth can easily become a bottleneck.
Any question?
OK, so let's get to vector processing in more depth until we get to the break, but then we can
continue later on.
OK, so we discuss about vector registers.
Each vector data register holds NN bit values.
We also have vector control registers like vector lengths, vector strides, these two you have seen
before.
We also have another vector control register which we call it vector mask.
So with vector mask you can actually indicate which elements of vector to operate on.
So you have vector lengths of let's say 16, meaning that you want to do operation on 16 data
elements.
But in some cases you don't want to do that addition across all these 16.
So for example you want to do that addition only for the first half of them like for only for the
eight first elements.
So then you can set a vector mask which has the 1st 8 bit is 1 and that the second 8 bit is 0.
So with that vector mask you can control the operation that you do only addition on the half of the
vector registers that you have.
So vector mask is actually very important.
And with vector mask you can actually implement some sort of if you know if and else whatever.
When you have in your code, you can control manipulate with this vector mask in order to implement
conditional branches.
Essentially it has been called in in this context actually by predication.
So by vector mask, you are predicating some of the operations.
It's different from branch prediction.
Here we are doing branch predication.
So I'm just saying this, you know terminology for you as well because you're going to see it also
later as well.
OK, so and we have vector functional units here.
For example, we have 6 stage multiply pipeline.
So these two vector registers are feeding data to these multiply units and essentially you can use a
deep pipeline to execute element operation and fast clock cycles.
OK.
And we already discussed about that control of deep pipeline here is easy, easier compared to
general purpose processor.
OK, so I'm going to show quickly some example SIMD architecture that we have had in the past and
then we're going to get to the break actually.
So this one is crayon Cray actually was one of the let's say amazing architectures that they have
started using this SIMD architectures and also from the get go they combine SIMD pipeline as well
as a scalar pipeline.
So we have they have had both exactly because of the fact that not all part of the application is
data have data parallel.
So you need to be able to run scalar operation as well as data, data level, data parallel
operations.
So in Crave 1, here are some, you know, description of Crave one.
You don't need to memorise any of them, just showing them.
So for example, they have 16 memory banks and why we need 16 memory banks or why we need a lot of
memory banks we're going to see later.
Also, they had 864 bit scalar registers and they had 864 element vector registers in Crave 1.
And here's also a paper from Cray One computer system, which you can also check if you're
interested.
How many of you have seen that in?
OK, interesting.
Last year when I asked, actually only a few of you said that, but it's good.
It's good that you've seen this Cray XMP in CAP.
I actually have a very good memory of this place.
I remember for one of the paper that we were working on in 2017, I had a very nice brainstorming
meeting with one of my colleagues exactly here we were sitting and discussing and we get to a nice
paper actually after that.
OK, so you can check create XMP this diagram if you're also interested.
There is not much to talk about it here.
Just for you For more information, you know some numbers about how many registers they have.
We're not going to question about that those actually.
So you can also check them if you're interested.
And I leave you here, you can think about this question then we can discuss after break.
OK, so let's get back in 15 minutes at 3:15 and we will continue.
So yeah, let's continue.
Seymour Craig was the leader in supercomputer design and he was actually kind of a principled
architecture.
So he asked this question that if you were if you were plowing a field which we would rather use too
a strong oxen or 1024 chickens.
When I was studying in my university, I heard this actually in a little bit different like 2
elephants and 1024 mice, but I think this is the original 1.
So.
Well, yeah.
And the answer to this question, I don't think there is actually a definite answer to this one.
But the answer to this actually cause different ways of designing supercomputing supercomputers.
There are supercomputers that they are combining different large cores like accents, like several
accents, and also supercomputers that they have a lot of chickens, OK?
Like like when you think about GPUs, they're actually more in the line of chickens.
So there are a lot of small cores, 1000 of small cores but also in GPUs you have a big course and
each big, each big cores are considered of a lot of small course.
So in the end you can also think of combining these two paradigm.
But it also depends on the way of your parallelise.
So if your application have massively amount of data level parallelise that you are able to
distribute the load of execution across a lot of tiny task, then you might be able to actually get
much better performance with a lot of wimpy course.
However, when your application are not that parallel, you have some parallels but you cannot really
embarrassingly parallel it, parallelise it, then you might be able to use whether to use a strong
big course like oxen in this example.
But anyway, it's fun to think about this question actually a lot.
OK, so we've seen a lot here about the number of memory banks.
And let's see why we need a lot of banks for the memory.
So essentially in in vector processor, we need to it requires loading and storing multiple elements.
And essentially we need to provide good memory bands, elements separated from each other by a
constant distance, which we talk about is a stride.
And for now, we can consider that the stride is 1.
So elements can be loaded in consecutive cycles if we can start the load of one element per cycle.
So that's what we are trying to achieve.
So then we can sustain a throughput of one element per cycle.
So now the question is that how do we achieve this with the memory that takes more than one cycle to
access?
So if you have your memory takes let's say element cycles, then how you're going to get to this
throughput of one element per cycle.
So that's how we handle it with banking.
So we bank the memory and we interleave the elements across banks.
So here is an example how we do it.
So memory is divided into banks that can be that can be accessed independently and banks share
address and data buses.
So this is to reduce memory chip pins.
So banking is different from adding ports.
So you still have, you can have share ports, you can have share essentially you know, address buses,
data buses.
But then you can actually reduce, you know some you can try to interleave loading instructions.
So we can start and complete one bank access per cycle.
So this can sustain N concurrent accesses if all N go to different banks.
So if you don't have bank conflicts, let's say, and you all these concurrent accesses goes to
different banks, then you are able to sustain the throughput that you're looking for.
So essentially the next address is previous address plus the stride.
So if the stride is 1 and the consecutive elements interleave across banks and also number of banks
is greater or equal than bank latency, then we can sustain one element per cycle throughput.
And why is that?
So here we have 16 banks.
Assuming that the latency that you have is less than 16, let's say 11.
So you access the bank 0 for the first for the first element and then the second element you go to
the bank one.
Sorry, Yeah, Bank one then, then bank 234 and then at some point when you get to the essentially
bank actually in order to see the limit, let's assume that the the bank latency is 16, then it's we
can actually see the limit better.
So if the bank latency is 16, then the first element goes here and it's going to take 16 cycles to
be ready, right.
So The thing is that and then other elements, the 15 elements, they're going to go to the next other
banks like bank 123 until bank 15th, OK.
And when we want to access this bank 0 again for the 16th element, the previous one is done because
you already spent 16 cycles, so you don't have bank conflict.
So the other one doesn't need to wait.
So you can keep accessing.
So clearly, if you have memory access latency, which is less than the number of banks, then you
don't have this problem.
OK, you can sustain that troop.
So there is a bit different when you have different strides which we're going to see that like if
our stride is not one, then what would happen?
We're going to get to that later.
OK, so let's any question about banking actually makes sense.
OK, good.
So let's get to this example.
We want to see the performance of, you know, this scalar code and how we can increase it with vector
processors.
So the scalar code that we have here for this, you know this for loop that we discussed about it
before.
So this is the assembly code of it.
You have some you move, you know R0 reset it 50 because R0 is going to control the number of
iterations for your loop.
And you also the load the address of array A to register one, Rab to register 2 and array C to
register 3.
And essentially every in this loop, every cycle, sorry, in each iteration you do 2 loads.
So you load A and you load B.
And here is also we are using this auto auto increment addressing.
So you basically you do memory R1 plus plus, meaning that when you load, you also increment the
address such can be used for the next iteration.
OK, so essentially this load AI and BI and then you do this addition and basically you shift it to
right by 1 to divide it by two and then you store it.
OK and then essentially you check the branch condition and you need to loop for 50 times.
OK, so this is assembly code of like syntax is not important here.
You just think about it like this is the way that you're going to write it, for example, probably
more or less in MIPS for example.
OK, so here also we write the latency of these instructions, these simple instructions, they are all
one cycle.
Load instruction is 11, these load also 11, store is also 11, Addition is 4 cycles, shift is one
cycle and this branch is 2 cycles.
OK, so the first question I would ask is what's the number of dynamic instructions that we have
here?
Anyone how many instructions are we executing?
Now the number of static instruction here is 567-8910.
We have 10 static instructions, but how many dynamic instruction we have?
Like how many instructions are we executing?
Yes, the top 4 + 50 * 6 below.
Yes, which 304, right?
Yes, 304 dynamic instructions we are we are executing here.
OK, so that's the number of dynamic instructions.
Let's get to performance of this code in a scalar code execution time in order like forget about out
of order execution for simplicity here a scalar execution time on an in order processor with only
one bank.
So the first 2 loads here, they cannot be pipeline because you have only one.
One bank.
So you need to spend 2 * 11 cycles.
So essentially you spend 11 cycles for this load, 11 cycle here, then four cycle here, one cycle
here, 11:00 and 2:00.
So this whole is going to be 4040 cycles in each iteration.
So then the latency is going to be 50 * 40 because that loop is going to be executed 50 times +4 and
this 4 is the initial time OK.
So the latency is going to be 2004 cycles.
If you try to add you know banking like still you have one bank but you add 2 memory ports.
So now you can actually pipeline the first or you can also consider multiple two banks.
OK, so with that you can pipeline the 1st 2 loads.
So the latency of completion of these two loads is going to be 1 + 11 + 1.
OK.
So the the 1st 2 loads is going to be completed in 12 cycles like the first iteration.
And then if you calculate it's going to be 12 + 4 + 1 + 11 and +2 is going to be 30.
So 30 * 50 + 4 is going to be 1500 four.
OK, so that's, that's an improvement with banking that we're getting even in a scalar processor
aspect.
So now let's get to, you know, how would be the performance of it in a CMD operation?
Vectorizable loops.
So here a loop is vectorizable because each iteration is independent of any other and we can easily
vectorize it.
So essentially we move vector links of 50 because we want to operate on 50 array elements or vector
elements and also our stride is also one so vector stride is 1.
So then we load vector 0 of array A and vector one as array B, and then we do vector addition and
then we do vector shift rights, which element wise, right?
And then we store vector 3 to array C OK, So by doing that, actually you're really executing 7
instructions.
So that's a very important thing that we have here with SIMD that we are reducing the number of
dynamic instructions, which that immediately translates to less overhead, you know, for fetching
decoding of instructions.
So what was the performance of them assuming no chaining, We're going to see chaining.
But essentially you can chain vector elements together, vector functional unit together to get
better performance.
So you can think of chaining as data forwarding pass in the end.
And also, yeah, so, so the chaining actually definition is here.
Output of a vector functional unit cannot be used as the direct input of another.
So that's the definition of no chaining.
So and also the entire vector register needs to be ready before any element of it can be used as
part of another operation.
So there's also another assumption here with no chain.
And also we have one memory port and we have 16 memory banks.
So this is going to be the performance of this execution.
So you need to spend the 21 cycles, OK for the first this stride and vector lengths.
And then you spend 11 cycles for the first element of the load.
And then every cycle you're going to get the another one.
OK, so 49 cycles.
So you you need to load 50 elements, right?
So the first element you need to spend 11 cycles and then the rest is only 49.
So this is going to be end of this is going to be end of the first load and therefore the second
load again 111 and then 49.
And then vector addition is going to for the first element is going to be 4 cycles.
But then since you have a pipeline, it's going to be 49 for the rest.
And then vector shift is going to be 1 and then 49 for the rest.
And then and then now you need to store again 1st 11 cycles and then you need pipeline need.
So 49 cycles makes sense.
So if you sum it up, it's going to be 285 cycles, which huge improvement compared to, you know the
performance of the previous scalar operations.
So why 16 banks?
Because the memory access latency is 11 cycle.
And we kind of like to have, you know, the number of banks as a 2 to the power something because
then you can easily also design the.
And multiplexers and so, OK, so if the stride is bigger than one, then we might have some problems.
Basically what if the stride is bigger than one, what would be the number of banks in order to
ensure that we can handle this 11 cycle latency?
So that's the question and you can actually think about it and prove it.
It's not hard, but as long as these destroyed your stride and also the number of banks are
relatively prime to each other, then you can and also your the number of banks are bigger than the,
the bank, the bank latency, you're able to sustain that throughput.
So in the end, it's important to be.
So when the stride is 1, everything to 1 is relatively prime, right?
But when your stride is not one, then you need to be careful with your number of banks to be still
prime with that stride.
But I mean that also is fun to check later if you're interested.
OK, so with vector chaining we can do data forwarding from one vector function unit to another.
Essentially when we are done by loading the first elements, we can start sending it to the, you
know, to the multiplication unit.
So that's a change.
So we don't need to wait until one operation is completely done until we go to the next 1.
So it's very similar to forwarding pass that we have in out of order machine as well.
So with vector chaining still we cannot do the 1st 2 loads, you know, in completely parallel because
we have only one memory load.
So essentially you need to do, yeah, you need to wait for 11 cycle here and then 49 cycles and then
eleven cycle.
But here after 11 cycles, you have the two first elements of, I mean the two first elements of A&B
are ready.
So you can immediately go to the multiplication, sorry, addition.
So that's why immediately from here, from this point, actually you go to the addition part.
So you don't, you don't need to wait until you're done by 49 and then it start addition.
So that's the difference that chaining provides for us.
So you initiate the addition here and after four cycle, when you're done by addition, you can
immediately go to the shift, right?
And but after one cycle here you're done.
But you cannot start storing because your memory port is not ready because you have only one memory
port.
So you need to wait until this part that you're done by the second load and then you can start the
storing.
So if you basically sum them up, you're going to get to 882 cycles.
And I already explained why we have these two vector loads, they cannot be pipeline and why we
cannot start storing before, you know, immediately here.
So essentially we have this strict assumption that each memory bank has a single port here in this
example.
So if you can increase the number of ports, so if you are we can do chaining and also we can have
two load ports and one is store port in each bank, then yeah, then we can actually get amazing
performance.
So here essentially by the by first one of your load port you start loading A and for this by the
second load port you're starting loading B.
So you only need to wait one cycle here and then you start loading B.
So by here you can start addition and then you can do shifting and then you can also start a storing
because I mean after this because you are also have a specific store port.
So whenever you're ready, you can do a store.
OK.
So if you have that, you know, pay the cost, then your latency is going to be 79 cycles, which is
great.
And that is like more around 19 times performance improvement compared to the scalar operation.
OK.
So I recommend you check this, you know, diagram also at home.
It's not magic, but just to understand how things are working.
But yeah, in the end, the more you pay, like when you add more ports, you can, you are able to
pipeline more and then you get better performance.
OK, so now we want to get to some.
Is there any question about this part?
Yes.
Could you just quickly explain again how memory plans and memory ports interact with each other?
Yeah, so I.
I think memory banks is a let's say cost efficient way of adding ports.
So when you when you so you, when you, when you want to have you can add 2 ports and that would
would be amazing.
But then the cost of adding two ports is much more compared to adding two banks.
And The thing is that adding banks is much more scalable compared to adding ports.
So you can easily go to 16 banks, 32 banks, but you cannot really add.
So here having two load ports is OK, but if you want to have like, I don't know, 16 ports is really
not possible because of the cost.
So yeah, but when you have different ports, you can think of, OK, I have different ports, I can do
everything completely in parallel.
But when you add banks, you're doing it in a consecutive way, you know, So that's also another
difference.
So this so with banks you can think of pipelining, you know, good question.
Any other questions?
OK, So what if the number of data elements is bigger than number of elements in vector registers?
So in the previous example we considered, OK, I can set vector link to whatever number I want.
So we had 50 and we just set vector lengths to 50.
But what if the maximum possible vector lengths that we might have is like 32?
Then what should we do?
So the idea is that we need to break loops so that each iteration operates on number of elements in
the vector register.
For example, when we have 527 data elements and 64 elements vector registers, then we can have 8
iterations where vector lengths is 64.
And then and in the end we need to have one iteration when the when vector lengths is 15.
So we need to change vector lengths for the last iteration.
So that's actually it's called vector stream mining, which actually get inspired by this surface
mining or stream mining.
You can check with this wiki information if you're interested.
OK, so yeah, I think this is, this makes sense, right?
It's not, it's not that much, you know, hard to image.
Another question is that what if the vector data is not stored in a strided fashion in memory.
So we would love to have it in a strided fashion like everything we want to have it in a consecutive
manner.
But there might be some cases that essentially we have we need to operate on irregular memory access
to the vector.
And these are not very good for CMD.
But there might be some cases in your application that some parts you need to do that.
But majority of the part you don't need to do that.
So you can still do it irregular memory access to a vector.
So how we do it, we essentially use indirection to do combine and pack elements into vector
registers, which is called scatter gather operations.
So essentially when we want to before starting the operation, we gather different part of the memory
into the vector register from different addresses.
We just load them and gather them to vector registers and we operate on those vector registers.
And when we are done and we want to store, we might want to store in different locations in not
consecutive manner.
So that is called a scatter.
So you use a pointer, you know store pointers to see where you want to store.
So doing so actually helps with avoiding useless computation on sparse vectors.
So now it is also with machine learning you know that there might be a lot of instead of having
dense matrix matrix multiplication, might be sparse matrix matrix multiplication.
And actually doing sparse operation are not very handy and good for SIMD pipelines.
They they actually prefer to have dense matrices.
But having dense is also not very good because then you are wasting a lot of you know the
computation.
So that's why you need to have find some way to handle the sparse operations in the CMD operations.
So how we do it here?
Here is an example for gather operation.
So we want to vectorise loops with indirect accesses like here.
The second, this one, the second operand is loading from array C, but the address that you want to
check is actually coming from another array.
OK, so it's kind of an indirect memory access.
So the way we do it, we actually use it with a gather operation.
So we load vector D Yeah, so we load exactly.
We load the the whole vector D to register D and then we need to have it have this instruction load
vector indirect.
So we indirect load to vector C from RC which RC is the the base address.
Of the vector C and also this VD which is the you know, the vector register for the for the operands
of the RAD OK.
And with that you can essentially load indirectly.
And after that you have your vector C ready.
And for vector B it's easy because it's a strided so you load it also and then you do addition and
then store OK.
So there is a special instruction like load indirect that you can use it for gathering operation
makes sense.
Similarly for storing you can have scatter.
So here for example you basically these are your data vector to store.
You have some values and you want to store them in your vector in the memory.
But the location that you want to store is actually coming from index vector.
So essentially you need to use indirect indexing for a store that such such such that you store this
value in base plus zero and then base plus one.
You don't change it because you don't have anything to say for base +2, you store 6.5 and so on and
so forth.
So that's also called scatter example.
So you need some specific instructions that can help you doing that.
OK, makes sense.
Very good.
Also how we handle conditional operations in a loop that I already also talked about it, we can use
mask operations using this V mask.
So here in this example, you, you you need to in each iteration you're checking a condition and
based on that you are doing some operation.
So we have this vector mask register is a bit mask determining which data elements should not be
acted upon.
So for example this example you load A to vector 0 and B to vector one and then you generate your
vector mask.
How we generate.
So we check this condition here.
Essentially if the element is not zero, we need to do this operation right.
So we generate V mask by saying that V mask equals to V-0 not equal of 0.
So those locations that V-0 which is array a is not zero, then V mask is going to be 1 for those
locations.
And then when you apply vector multiplication, it's going to be acted only on the locations that you
have mask 1.
You know you act on it for other locations.
Basically it just doesn't execute and then you store OK.
So that's mask operation which you can implement conditional branch.
So as I said, this is also called predicated execution.
Execution is predicated on mask bit OK, makes sense.
So here is also another example with masking you're it's kind of if and else.
So you compare A&B to get V mask and then we do the operation.
Yeah, So we first compare A&B in this location and then we do the operation based on the mask and
then we complete the V mask in order to do the else, OK.
And then we need to do the operation again.
So with that you can also implement if and else.
OK, how do we implement mask vector instructions?
There are two different ways or two, Yeah two different approach to implement in the in the real
hardware.
One would be that we execute all N operations, we just turn off the results, write back according to
mask.
So we do the for example multiplication for all elements.
But then if the mask is not active like if you need to, if we need to predicate that we basically we
don't write back it.
OK, so you just turn off it.
Another way would be density time implementation which we scan mask vector and only execute elements
with non 0 mask.
So here you're trying to be more intelligent and you'd only do operations on locations that you need
to do.
OK, so which one is better?
Again, it depends on the on your mask.
Essentially if you have most of your mask is actually 1, so you're going to do actually for most of
them.
You might prefer actually this simple implementation because it's much easier and faster to do.
But if you if you have a lot of location that you don't want to do operation like 50% of it, just
you know a number, then you might prefer to have this kind of implementation.
So in the end it depends, OK, it depends on your mask and also the application and which one is
better.
You can also have combination of both at the same time.
In your hardware as well.
OK, so we already discussed about this stride and bank count.
So I said as long as a stride and bank count are relatively prime to each other and there are enough
banks to cover bank access latency, we can sustain one element per cycle throughput.
So this is good.
But then the problem is coming when we have, you know, row major and column major and we are
operating on matrixes, matrixes.
So we already seen this, you know, example.
So now we have different strides, OK.
And once you have different strides, what would be the number of banks, you know, to be relatively
prime, It's going to be a bit difficult here, you know, to avoid, to avoid bank conflicts.
So having different strides actually can complicate things and also different operations of loads B
actually they can have conflicts with load operation of A.
You may say that we are not going to pipeline them, but if you want to pipeline A&B, then you might
have bank conflicts as well.
I mean, you do want to pipeline them because you want to, you know, have a better performance.
But since A&B have different strides, then you might have some conflicts between B and A when you're
loaded.
OK, so how do we minimise the bank conflicts?
There are different ways we can add more banks of course, which is we've been doing that.
Also, we can add more ports to each bank that can also provide weather, of course, performance and
minimise overhead.
We can try to have better data layout to match the access pattern, but it's also very limited.
It depends on the application that you have and how much you know, you know, you know how much you
are.
You have this freedom to put data, you know, in different locations to minimise bank conflicts.
And I should say that actually this part is actually one of the one of the things that actually
programmers, you know, expert programmers, they are spending a lot of time on it like a lot of
people are programming with GPUs.
And in GPU also we have shared memory which called also scratch pad memory.
And actually it's better to call as a scratch pad memory.
NVIDIA calls it as shared memory, which is not a great terminology.
It's actually a scratch pad memory software, managed cache and program is actually they have to
spend a lot of time to put data nicely to avoid bank conflicts in that shared memory.
So that part actually it's something that programmers or compilers can do a lot work on it, but at
some point it's not possible.
So you're limited in the end.
There are also better mapping of address to bank.
So, so far we are trying to, you know, have very simple way of mapping addresses to bank, but it can
be also kind of randomised mapping.
So based on your address.
So usually what we have learnt is that based on the address we use, some bits of the address might
be low significant bits, might be high most significant bits and then based on those bits we decide
which bank we want to access.
OK, it can be also randomised.
So there are this is nice paper that you can also check which essentially we do pseudo randomly
interleaved memory.
So with that you might be able to minimise also bank conflicts with the but also it comes at some
price of you know like determining the the bank location is not that easy.
Now you need to do a function, OK?
In the end, it comes with some overhead at this in the end.
OK, So you can also check this beautiful paper from ISCA regarding this pseudorandom, the interlaved
memory.
Any question?
OK, so this array and vector processor, let's revisit them again.
Now the distinction that we actually discuss is actually kind of purist distinction and the most
modern SIMD processor are actually combination of both, as we also, you know, kind of talk about
it.
They exploit data paralysing both time and space and GPUs are a prime example that we will cover
next week.
So here's just a recall regarding array and vector processor.
So how are we going to combine them?
Here we have this vector edition, and you might have only one lane of functional units.
You can think of it as a vector processor.
So each vector processor you can consider as a one lane of SIMD, OK.
Then you can actually have some other lanes as well in parallel.
So then now you're combining both paradigms.
So you're doing operations in a vector processor in one lane but at the same time you have several
lanes which you are doing it like a array processor array.
So in that way you can combine these two paradigm together in time and space.
And based on that, you can actually distribute your elements into different vector registers.
You can have elements 048, so on and so forth to this vector registers that operating on this lane.
And then you can have other elements like 159 to another lane, 2610 to another lane, and so on and
so forth.
So you need to have a statically mapped vector registers to different lanes in order to operate on
this.
You know, kind of a combination of vector and added process.
OK, does it make sense?
OK, so here's also another example.
You have, you have 8 lanes.
If I'm yes, you have 8 lanes here.
Yes, you have 8 lanes and you have 32 elements.
So essentially you do loads.
So 8 operation can be done in parallel completely because you have 8 lanes, but then rest is
consecutive and then you go, you know to the multiplication unit addition And with that you can
sustain 24 operations per cycle at a steady state.
For example, this architecture.
OK, so any question?
Good.
So now we also need to see how we need to do vectorise code.
And one way is that programmer tries to vectorise the codes, you know, but people also have been
looking into a lot how we can automatically vectorise the vectorise code.
And that needs essentially the compiler needs to you know, understand the code.
Sometimes you need to do a lot of reordering of operation sequencing to do to understand how we can
vectorise the code.
And that's not a easy task for compiler to do.
And that's why still they are not there even though we have auto vectorisable, you know compilers
that they are doing that, but in the end they are, their performance is very limited.
You know how much if the code is easy to understand, you know it's easy to vectorise.
But I would also say that those codes are also easy for programmers to vectorise them, OK.
Those codes that they are not easy to vectorise for programmers, they are also not easy for
compilers to vectorise.
So in the end, this automatic code vectorisation that there needs to be a lot more work to do in
that line.
OK, So yeah, let's summarise.
Vector and SIMD machines are good at exploiting regular data level.
Parallelies and some same operation perform on many data elements which improve performance,
simplify design and no intra vector dependences which avoids which low allows us to have deep
pipeline in the end and performance improvement limited by vectorizability of the code.
Scalar operations limited limit vector machine performance and that's why we always need to remember
Amdahl's law.
And also Crayvon was the fastest scalar matching at this time.
So even though Cray has been, you know, known as a vector processor or array processor machine, but
also Crayvon was the fastest scalar machine because they knew that in order to provide good
performance, they also need to have a good performance for sequential part of the code.
And that's why they have worked a lot on scalar operations as well.
And many existing IC include vector like SIMD operations like Intel MMXSSEAVEX, Power PC and ARM.
All of them they have SIMD extensions and SIMD instructions.
OK, so here's Amdo's law.
Let me check the time.
I think we still have some time to go over SIMD operations in mother IC as well quickly, but any
question before I jump into this topic.
OK, so this part is actually quite fun.
Interesting.
So basically people, vendors, they also wanted to add the SIMD operations because they realise you
know that we do need there are a lot of application that they are operating on vectors and it's
good to have SIMD extension.
So they are starting adding that and one of the first example was was the thing that have been done
in Intel and essentially what they have observed here is that we already have a pipeline that.
So when you have this register S0 or S1 for example here this actually yeah.
So you have a 32 bits.
When you want to add these two, you can actually chunk these register into 4 partitions and if you
make sure that you don't propagate the carry for each 8 bits to the next one, then you can have a
separate addition.
OK, so this is called pack addition 8 bit which you can do.
So you still need to modify ALU to eliminate these carries between 8 bit values.
But with that if you do that, then you are able to do this pack addition operation in a kind of a,
you know, element wise addition which each element is 8 bit and you do this addition 8 bit by 8
bit.
OK, if you carry, if you propagate the carry, you're going to have the addition of these two 32 bit,
32 bit values.
But if you don't propagate, then you're going to have essentially addition of each 8 bit element.
So with that Intel Pentium MMX, for example, they use this kind of, you know, insight and they have
this one instruction operates on multiple data elements simultaneously.
It was actually more or less in the line of array processing, but much more limited.
And they designed with multiple Dr.
graphics operation in mind.
So here essentially there were no vector lengths registers and op code of the instruction determines
data type.
So based on some instruction based on the OP code, it might be 88 bit bytes, or it might be 416 bit
words, or 232 bit double words, or 164 bit quad word.
So based on the op code, you can decide how many elements vector elements you're operating on.
And a stride is always equal to 1.
So that's MMX here also shows the vector register.
You know how you can partition it into 842 or 1:00?
Then you can have different operation like packed compare greater than 1.
So you compare it, you know, packed in 4/4 in 4 partitions and you calculate this, you know, mask
essentially.
You can also have this packed multiply and add which is used for dot product essentially.
You can also have this diagram for matrix vector multiply.
So it's not that hard to imagine about it.
But it's also interesting to to see about this example which actually has been presented in this
paper.
So there is a picture of this this lady with a background which supposed to be blue, but you know
the the copy that we had wasn't blue.
So this background is blue and then you you have another image which is a bluesome background and
you want to essentially have the background of this lady with a bluesome background essentially.
OK, so you can actually implement it nicely with these operations.
You essentially first generate the mask.
So for those parts that you know, you first have a array which completely blue and then you compare
your your own image with blue.
OK, So if it's if it's not blue, then you're here you put zero if it's blue, you put full one.
OK, So for example, this one the pixel is blue, then I have full 1 and so on and so forth.
And based on this mask that you generated, you can do this operation.
So you first do hand of this bluesome picture with this mask.
So for those parts that you have full 1, the output is going to be this bluesome picture OK, the
pixel of bluesome and the other parts which the mask was complete zero then the and operation is
going to be 0.
So you have 00 and then bluesome pixel and then 00 then you can do you can yeah, this do and
operation, but not it like in and operation.
So you yeah, so you essentially you generate yeah, the output for those parts that they are 0 here
you need to have this pixel of the the original photo.
And then you need to essentially order these two output together.
So you order them and then you have the output, OK.
And then you have this change of the background.
And here also the pseudo code of it.
So you can also check it if you're interested and some writing about Internet.
There are also some other extension in IS AM MX was the first one, SSE is the latest another version
of it which they added double precision floating point and they added also AVX later for you know
more fuse, multiply, add and then also a mix which is advanced.
Extension and that's all about it and there are some slides after that regarding you know SIMD in
modern also accelerators which might get to that later next week as well.
I think have a nice weekend because tomorrow is also holiday and see you next week.
Thank you.